A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Mexico City Field Office Program and Subject Files FA1530
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Central America Programs, 1962-1983; 2; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  - Human Rights, 1979-1983; 5
    The Ford Foundation's human rights program began in 1980 and served grantees in Central America who, according to selection criteria established by the Mexico City Office, qualified as intellectual refugees. Between 1980 and 1982, thirty refugees were awarded grants. These awardees were university professors and administrators, but the program was also open to journalists, writers, and labor union workers. Most of these grantees designed research proposals dealing with their professional background with the purpose of locating gainful employment in the country of exile.
    - Human Rights, 1979 (Box 20, Folder 242)
    - Human Rights, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 243)
    - Human Rights, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 244)
    - Human Rights, 1982-1983 (Box 20, Folder 245)
  - Law and Society, 1970-1982; 6
    - Faculty of Law, University of Costa Rica, 1970-1972 (Box 20, Folder 246)
    - Law and Society, 1976-1982 (Box 20, Folder 247)
  - Population, 1967-1978; 7
    - ALACODE, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 248)
    - ADC - Associacion Demografica Costarricense (Costa Rican Demographic Association), 1974-1978 (Box 21, Folder 249)
    - APROFAM Asociacion Pro-Bienestar de la Familia de Guatemala, 1972-1974 (Box 21, Folder 250)
    - Communication Radio, 1975 November (Box 21, Folder 251)
    - Costa Rica, 1972-1976 (Box 21, Folder 252)
    - Costa Rica Regional Training Program in Family Planning - Communications, 1971 January-November (Box 21, Folder 253)
    - Costa Rica Regional Training Program in Family Planning - Communications, 1971-1972 (Box 21, Folder 254)
    - El Salvador, 1969-1976 (Box 21, Folder 255)
    - Guatemala, 1968-1976 (Box 21, Folder 256)
    - Honduras, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 257)
    - Nicaragua, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 258)
    - Panama, 1967-1977 (Box 21, Folder 259)
    - Population - General, 1968-1970 (Box 21, Folder 260)
    - University of Costa Rica - Non-Parametric Statistics Course, 1968-1970 (Box 21, Folder 261)
  - Rural Development, 1978-1981; 8
    - CEMAT - Centro de Estudios Mesoamericanos Sobre Tecnologia Apropiada, 1978-1980 (Box 21, Folder 262)
    - CINASE - Centro de Investigacion y Asesoria Socio-Economica, 1978-1981 (Box 21, Folder 263)
  - Social Science, 1968-1982; 9
    - Fundacion Salvadorena de Desarrollo y Vivienda Mínima, 1973-1978 (Box 22, Folder 264)
    - ICAP - Instituto Centroamericano de Administración Pública, 1975-1982 (Box 22, Folder 265)
    - INCAP - Instituto de Nutricion de Centroamerica y Panama, 1975-1979 (Box 22, Folder 266)
    - SIECA - Secretariat for the Economic Integration of Central America, 1977-1979 (Box 22, Folder 267)
    - Social Sciences, 1968-1971 (Box 22, Folder 268)
    - Solidarios, 1976-1981 (Box 22, Folder 269)
    - Universidad Centroamericana (Managua, Nicaragua), 1977-1978 (Box 22, Folder 270)
  - Urban and Regional Planning, 1968-1969; 10
    - Urban/Regional Planning, 1968 March-July (Box 22, Folder 271)
    - Urban/Regional Planning, 1968-1969 (Box 22, Folder 272)
- Caribbean Programs, 1964-1982; 3; 1.79 Cubic Feet 4 containers
  - General, 1968-1982; 1
    - Caribbean - General, 1968-1974 (Box 22, Folder 273)
    - Caribbean - General, 1975-1982 (Box 22, Folder 274)
    - Cuba, 1977-1980 (Box 23, Folder 275)
  - Agriculture, 1968-1975; 2
    - Dominican Republic - General, 1968-1973 (Box 23, Folder 276)
    - Agriculture - General, 1973-1975 (Box 23, Folder 277)
    - Fundacion Promotora de Cooperativas and Universidad José Simeón Cañas (El Salvador), 1973-1974 (Box 23, Folder 278)
    - Jamaica Agriculture and Nutrition Program, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 279)
    - ISA - Instituto Superior de Agricultura (Dominican Republic), 1968-1974 (Box 23, Folder 280)
  - Education, 1968-1974; 3
    - African Caribbean Cultural Influences, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 281)
    - Jamaica - General, 1968-1973 (Box 23, Folder 282)
    - UNICA Conference (COLABORA), 1973-1974 (Box 23, Folder 283)
    - UNICA - Project Proposal, 1974 (Box 23, Folder 284)
      Empty except for cross reference sheet - look in Log File L74-287
    - University of the West Indies, 1968-1970 (Box 23, Folder 285)
  - Population, 1964-1976; 4
    - Guyana, 1974-1976 (Box 23, Folder 286)
    - Barbados, 1964-1974 (Box 23, Folder 287)
    - Caribbean, 1967-1970 (Box 23, Folder 280)
    - Dominican Republic - National Population Council, 1967-1972 (Box 24, Folder 281)
    - Evaluation and Statistics, undated (Box 24, Folder 282)
      Empty except for cross reference sheet - refer to Problems in Introducing an Evaluation System: The Jamaican Experience, April 1970
    - French Islands - (Guadeloupe & Martinique), 1969-1972 (Box 24, Folder 283)
    - Haiti - Centre d'Hygiene Familiale, 1970-1976 (Box 24, Folder 284)
    - Haiti, 1968-1976 (Box 24, Folder 285)
    - Haiti - Pathfinder Fund, 1969-1972 (Box 24, Folder 286)
    - Jamaica - General, 1967-1976 (Box 24, Folder 287)
    - Jamaica Family Planning Association, Ltd., 1967-1975 (Box 24, Folder 288)
    - Jamaica National Family Planning Board (JNFPB), 1968-1975 (Box 24, Folder 289)
    - Jamaica National Family Planning Board - Communications, 1969-1972 (Box 24, Folder 290)
    - Jamaica National Family Planning Board (NFPB) - Data Edward Ebanks' Consultantship, 1968-1970 (Box 24, Folder 291)
    - Leeward Islands (Antigua, Montserrat, St. Vincent), 1969-1970 (Box 24, Folder 292)
    - PAHO - Caribbean Health Ministers Conference, 1970 (Box 24, Folder 293)
    - U.S. Inst.: Princeton University and the Jamaica Manpower Research Unit, 1967-1972 (Box 24, Folder 294)
    - Trinidad, 1969-1974 (Box 24, Folder 295)
  - Social Science, 1969-1972; 5
    - U.S. Institutions - American Assembly, 1969-1972 (Box 25, Folder 296)
    - University of the West Indies, ISER, undated (Box 25, Folder 297)
      Empty except for cross reference sheets - refer to Grants - 06900589 and 06900589B
  - Urban Studies, 1967-1972; 6
    - Urban Studies, 1967-1972 (Box 25, Folder 298)
- Latin America Program, 1962-1984; 4; 3.89 Cubic Feet 1 legal document box and 9 letter document boxes
  - Agriculture, 1966-1972; 1
    - Agricultural Economics, 1970-1976 (Box 25, Folder 299)
    - Agriculture - Brazil, 1970-1975 (Box 25, Folder 300)
    - Agriculture - Chile, 1969-1975 (Box 25, Folder 301)
    - Agriculture - Colombia, 1969-1979 (Box 25, Folder 302)
    - Agricultural - Regional, 1971-1978 (Box 25, Folder 303)
    - Agriculture – Peru, 1967-1982 (Box 25, Folder 304)
    - Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical (CIAT), Part 1, 1974-1979 (Box 25, Folder 305)
    - Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical (CIAT), Part 2, 1966-1974 (Box 26, Folder 306)
    - Centro Internacional Para de Mejoramiento de Maiz y Trigo (CIMMYT), 1972-1980 (Box 26, Folder 307)
    - Grupo Internacional Para El Desarrollo Agricola En America Latina (CERIDA), 1977 (Box 26, Folder 308)
    - Agriculture Resources for the Future, Inc., 1972-1974 (Box 26, Folder 309)
    - Agriculture Resources for the Future, Inc., 1968-1971 (Box 26, Folder 310)
    - Socio-Economic Research Network, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 311)
    - Visit to Latin America by Professor Olayide, University of Ibadan (T and S Award - Nigeria Office), 1973-1974 (Box 26, Folder 312)
  - Anthropology, 1975-1980; 2
    - Anthropology – Regional Part One, 1977-1980 (Box 26, Folder 313)
    - Anthropology – Regional Part Two, 1975-1977 (Box 26, Folder 314)
  - Education, 1962-1979; 3
    - Conferences and Seminars - Regional, 1969-1979 (Box 26, Folder 315)
    - Educational Television (ETV) Latin American Association (Lic. Maximo Salinas), 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 316)
    - Instituto Panamericano de Alta Direccion de Empresa (IPADE), 1966-1976 (Box 27, Folder 317)
    - Preschool Education - General, 1970-1971 (Box 27, Folder 318)
    - Programmed Instruction - General, 1969-1970 (Box 27, Folder 319)
    - Ford Foundation Study of Education - Attachment, undated (Box 27, Folder 320)
      Cross reference sheets
    - Educational Testing Service, 1962-1963 (Box 27, Folder 321)
    - OLAC Training Inventory, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 322)
    - IIE - Institute of International Education, 1963-1966 (Box 27, Folder 323)
    - Latin American Teaching Fellowship Program (LATFP), 1972-1977 (Box 27, Folder 324)
    - Latin American Teaching Fellowship - General, 1967-1971 (Box 27, Folder 325)
    - US Institutes – Institute of Current World Affairs, 1970-1972 (Box 27, Folder 326)
    - Peruvian National Universities Council, 1969 (Box 27, Folder 327)
    - Regional Volume 1, 1975-1978 (Box 27, Folder 328)
    - Education - Peru, 1967-1970 (Box 27, Folder 329)
    - UNESCO (General), 1970-1972 (Box 28, Folder 330)
    - Universidad Metropolitana Venezuela, 1968-1972 (Box 28, Folder 331)
    - US Institution Foreign Area Fellowship Program, 1973 (Box 28, Folder 332)
  - Human Rights and Displaced Scholars, 1973-1980; 4
    - Human Rights and Displaced Scholars, 1973-1974 (Box 28, Folder 333)
    - Human Rights and Displaced Scholars, 1976-1977 (Box 28, Folder 334)
    - Human Rights and Displaced Scholars, 1978-1979 (Box 28, Folder 335)
    - Human Rights and Displaced Scholars, 1979 (Box 28, Folder 336)
    - Human Rights and Displaced Scholars, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 337)
  - International Relations, 1973-1978; 5
    - Hemispheric International Relations, 1976-1977 (Box 28, Folder 338)
    - Hemispheric International Relations, 1978-1981 (Box 28, Folder 339)
    - Inter-American Development Bank, 1973-1985 (Box 28, Folder 340)
    - Hemispheric International Relations, 1975-1976 (Box 29, Folder 341)
    - Hemispheric International Relations, 1978 (Box 29, Folder 342)
  - Population, 1970-1980; 6
    - Population - Regional, 1973-1980 (Box 29, Folder 343)
    - Population - Ford/Rockefeller Program, 1973-1976 (Box 29, Folder 344)
    - Population - Ford/Rockefeller Program, 1977 (Box 29, Folder 345)
    - Population - Ford/Rockefeller Program, 1978 January-July (Box 29, Folder 346)
    - Population - Ford/Rockefeller Program, 1978-1980 (Box 30, Folder 347)
    - Ford/Rockefeller Award - Rogelio Diaz-Guerrero, 1973-1975 (Box 30, Folder 348-350)
    - Ford/Rockefeller Program - Attachment Folders, 1975-1978 (Box 30, Folder 351-353)
    - Colombia, 1970-1979 (Box 31, Folder 354)
    - Population Consultants, 1972-1976 (Box 31, Folder 355)
    - Population, Volume III, 1973-1976 (Box 31, Folder 356)
  - Resources and the Environment, 1970-1980; 7
    - Resources and the Environment, 1970-1980 (Box 31, Folder 357)
  - Rural Development, 1973-1980; 8
    - Rural Development, Volume I, 1975-1978 (Box 31, Folder 358)
    - Rural Development, Volume II, 1974-1975 (Box 31, Folder 359)
    - Rural Development, Volume III, 1978-1979 (Box 31, Folder 360)
    - Rural Development - Colombia (Part I), 1978-1980 (Box 31, Folder 361)
    - Rural Development - Colombia (Part II), 1973-1978 (Box 32, Folder 362)
  - Science and Technology, 1967-1973; 9
    - Science and Engineering - General, 1967-1973 (Box 32, Folder 363)
  - Social Sciences, 1965-1981; 10
    - Consejo Latinoamericano de Ciencias Sociales (CLACSO) - Comisión de Estudios Rurales, 1976-1981 (Box 32, Folder 364)
    - Andean Region, Volume 1, 1977-1978 (Box 32, Folder 365)
    - CLASCO - Regional (Vol. I), 1971-1977 (Box 32, Folder 366)
    - CLASCO - Regional (Vol. II), 1977-1978 (Box 32, Folder 367)
    - FLACSO - Regional, 1973-1979 (Box 32, Folder 368)
    - Social Sciences - Meetings (Part I), 1977-1979 (Box 33, Folder 369)
    - Social Sciences - Meetings (Part II), 1976 (Box 33, Folder 370)
    - Peru Meetings, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 371)
      Cross reference sheets to reports
    - Peru Meetings, 1973-1976 (Box 33, Folder 372)
    - Social Sciences, 1978-1979 (Box 33, Folder 373)
    - Social Sciences - Regional, 1965-1977 (Box 33, Folder 374)
  - Urban Studies, 1967-1984; 11
    - Urban/Regional Planning, 1967-1969 (Box 34, Folder 375)
    - Urban Studies: Latin America, 1968-1974 (Box 34, Folder 376)
- International Programs, 1966-1981; 5; 1.71 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes and 1 half-box
  - Agriculture, 1973-1981; 1
    - Agriculture: Ford Foundation International, 1973-1981 (Box 34, Folder 377)
    - Office of Latin America and Caribbean/Middle East and Africa Program Advisors in Agriculture Meeting, 1973-1974 (Box 34, Folder 378)
  - Communication, 1979; 2
    - Communications: International, 1979 (Box 34, Folder 379)
  - Economics, 1975-1978; 3
    - International Economic Order Research Competition, 1975-1978 (Box 34, Folder 380)
  - Education, 1968-1978; 4
    - Eisenhower Fellowship Program - General, 1968-1972 (Box 34, Folder 381)
    - Delhi Education Meeting - Papers and Comments, 1971-1972 (Box 34, Folder 382, Box 35, Folder 383)
    - International Division Education Meeting, September 1975 (Box 35, Folder 384)
    - International Institute of Communications, 1977-1978 (Box 35, Folder 385)
    - Ford Foundation - Latin America, Asia and Europe - Colombia, Chile, and Lima, 1974-1976 (Box 35, Folder 386-387)
  - Foundations, 1976-1980; 5
    - Foundations - General, 1976-1980 (Box 35, Folder 388)
  - Population, 1972-1982; 6
    - International Committee on the Management of Population Programmes, 1975-1979 (Box 35, Folder 389)
    - Population, 1972-1979 (Box 35, Folder 390)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1974-1982 (Box 35, Folder 391)
  - Public Management, 1967-1979; 7
    - Public Management - Ford Foundation International, 1967-1979 (Box 35, Folder 392)
  - Resources and the Environment, 1973-1981; 8
    - Resources and the Environment, 1973-1980 (Box 36, Folder 393)
    - Resources for the Future, Inc., 1974-1981 (Box 36, Folder 394)
  - Rural Development, 1975-1981; 9
    - Rural Development - International, 1975-1981 (Box 36, Folder 395)
  - Science and Technology, 1975-1979; 10
    - Institute for Scientific and Technological Cooperation, 1978-1979 (Box 36, Folder 396)
    - Instituto Torcuato di Tella, 1976 (Box 36, Folder 397)
    - International Food Policy Research Institute, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 398)
  - Social Sciences, 1974-1980; 11
    - Social Sciences - Meetings, 1979 (Box 36, Folder 399)
    - Social Sciences Research Council, 1974-1980 (Box 36, Folder 400)
  - Conference Files, 1969-1975; 12
    - Latin America and Caribbean - Conference on Education Held in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 1973 May 14-16 (Box 36, Folder 401)
    - International Division Conference, 1975 September (Box 36, Folder 402)
      Empty except for cross reference sheet - see Log File L75-42
    - International Division Representatives Meeting - Mexico, 1969 December 2-5 (Box 36, Folder 403)
      Empty except for cross reference sheet - see Log File L69-167
  - Trip Files, 1966-1979; 13
    - David E. Bell and William D. Carmichael Visit - Visit to Mexico and Costa Rica, 1972 February-March (Box 36, Folder 404)
    - Harry Wilhelm Visit to Mexico, 1966 November 1-8 (Box 36, Folder 405)
      Sections include:
      Staff List
      Schedule
      Agriculture
      Education
      Population
      Science and Technology
      Social Sciences
      Grant Payments
    - Urban Studies - Study Project, 1970-1973 (Box 36, Folder 406)
    - U.S. Universities, 1976-1979 (Box 36, Folder 407)
    - Latin American and Caribbean - Education - Rio Education Meeting, 1971 (Box 36, Folder 408)
    - David Bell and Harry Wilhelm, 1967 February 18-25 (Box 37, Folder 409)
      Briefing Book sections include:
      1. Schedule
      2. Economic Data
      2a. Map of Mexico
      3. Gamble Letter
      4. Mexico Programs
      4b. Education
      4c. Population
      4d. Science and Technology
      4e. Social Sciences
      4f. Law, Government, and Management
      5. Financial Summary Mexico
      6. Financial Summary Central America
      7. Personnel - Mexico and Central America
    - Charles E. Wyzanski, Jr. Trip to Latin America, 1967-1968 (Box 37, Folder 410)
    - Charles E. Wyzanski, Jr. - Extracts of Letters, 1968 February 18-March 24 (Box 37, Folder 411)
    - Charles E. Wyzanski, Jr. - The Ford Foundation Briefing Book, Mexico and Central America, 1968 February 18-24 (Box 37, Folder 412)
    - Mr. and Mrs. David E. Bell and Harry Wilhelm - Visit to the Caribbean, 1968 November 24-December 5 (Box 37, Folder 413)
    - David E. Bell, Francis X. Sutton, and Harry Wilhelm - Mexico Trip, 1969 December 1-2 (Box 37, Folder 414)
    - David E. Bell and William D. Carmichael Visit to Mexico City - July 5-11, 1973 Briefing Book, 1973 July 5-11 (Box 37, Folder 415)
    - David E. Bell and William D. Carmichael Visit to Mexico, 1973 July 5-11 (Box 38, Folder 416)
    - Alexander Heard - Trustee Trip to Latin America, 1974 June 29-July 6 (Box 38, Folder 417)
    - McGeorge Bundy Trip, 1975 February 18-19 (Box 38, Folder 418)